<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, sent into England from the Summer Ilands. VVritten by Mr. Lewes Hughes, preacher of Gods Word there. 1615</title>
            <author>Hughes, Lewes, fl. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842049</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1177:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, sent into England from the Summer Ilands. VVritten by Mr. Lewes Hughes, preacher of Gods Word there. 1615</title>
                  <author>Hughes, Lewes, fl. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. B[eale] for William Welby, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Swanne in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The coppie of a letter, sent from Summer Ilands.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bermuda Islands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER, Sent into England from the SVMMER ILANDS.</p>
            <p>VVritten by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Lewes Hughes, Preacher of Gods Word there.</hi> 1615.</p>
            <p>¶ Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>I.B.</hi> for <hi>William Welby, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the</hi> Swanne in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1615.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:2"/>
            <head>The coppie of a Letter written by Lewes Hughes, <hi>Preacher of Gods Word</hi> in the
<hi>Summer Ilands,</hi> to his friends in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued friends, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Almighty God, in keeping theſe Ilands ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, from all people of the world (except ſome that haue come hither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their willes, to their loſſe, by meanes of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack) till now that it hath pleaſed his holy Maieſty, to diſcouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them vpon his people of <hi>England;</hi> is ſo great as ſhould ſtirre them vp with thankefull hearts, to praiſe his holy and great name, and to ſend ſuch to inhabit them as feare God, and giue themſelues to ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, that ſo, God may loue to dwell in thoſe Ilands, as hee did in
<hi>Sion,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>This is my reſt for euer, heere will I dwell: for I haue a delight therein. Pſal</hi> 132.13.14. And whereas it is giuen out by ſome, that wee doe
<pb facs="tcp:6672:3"/>wrong to the King of <hi>Spaine;</hi> they that thinke ſo, are in an errour. For the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> had neuer any thing to doe heere, and I hope neuer ſhall. The King of kings hath kept theſe Hands from the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> and all other kings in the world; till now, that it hath pleaſed his holy Maieſty to beſtow them vpon the King of <hi>England,</hi> and hath put vs his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in quiet poſſeſſion of them, without doing any wrong to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> or any other: and our hope is that if the Spaniards ſhall come to inuade vs, that God will not ſuffer them to take that from vs, that he hath freely giuen vs.</p>
            <p>It may be that ſom are afraid to com hither, becauſe of the ſtrange reports that haue gone of theſe Ilands; as that they are the Ilands of diuels, and that heere are ſtrange apparitions of diuels, and fearefull thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and lightening, as though Heauen and earth did meete together: beleeue me my beloued, here are no ſuch things (thankes be to God). True it is, that as almighty God did ſet the Cherubims, and the blade of a ſword ſhaking in fearefull manner to keepe
<hi>Adam</hi> from comming into Paradiſe: ſo by fearefull tempeſts, and terrible lightning and thunder, God hath terrified and kept all people of the world from comming into theſe Ilands to inhabit them, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by diuerſe ſignes of ſhipwrack, in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about the Ilands; and this, as I take it, is the cauſe that ſuch reports haue gone of theſe Ilands; and that all Nauigators and Mariners haue been carefull to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid and ſhunne them, as they would ſhunne the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell himſelfe: but now, ſince it hath pleaſed God, to diſcouer them vnto, and to beſtow them vpon his
<pb facs="tcp:6672:3"/>people of <hi>England,</hi> heere haue been no ſuch tempeſts nor danger, his holy and great name bee therefore pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed. And the more to ſtirre you vp to praiſe his hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> name: conſider, I pray you of the manner how he brought our men to the firſt ſight and true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them.</p>
            <p>He did not bring them to their loſſe and griefe, by ſhipwrack as he did others, but to their great ioy, in ſauing them from ſhipwrack: for our men were in danger of ſhipwrack, three daies before they came to the ſight of thoſe Ilands: I meane our men that were bound for
<hi>Virginia,</hi> in a Ship called the <hi>Sea-ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> with S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Gates,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>George Summers,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Newport,</hi> had their ſhip ſo ſhaken and torn with a cruell tempeſt, as ſhe receiued ſo much water as couered two tire of Hogſheads, aboue the ballaſt, ſo as men ſtood vp to the middles with buckets and kettles to baile out water, &amp; continually pumped for three daies and three nights together, the water not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding increaſing vpon them, and they ſo ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and out of hope, as they reſolued to ſhut vp the Hatches, and commit themſelues to the mercy of God. Some of them that had comfortable waters fetcht them out, and dranke one to an other, taking their laſt leaue one of an other, vntill their more ioyfull and happy meeting in Heauen.</p>
            <p>Then Sir <hi>George Summers</hi> ſitting vpon the poope of the ſhippe, where he ſat three daies and three nights without meat, couming the ſhip to keepe her as vpright as he could, did deſcry land, and called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people to follow their pumping and bailing out of water, which they did, the water ſtill increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb facs="tcp:6672:4"/>and the ſhip ready to ſinke into the bottome of the Sea.</p>
            <p>Then Almighty God, who is alwaies at hand rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to helpe in time of neede, did ſhew his mercy
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd power, in cauſing the Sea to be calme, and in keeping the ſhippe from ſinking, and in leading her ſafely to a ſafe place, where he lodged her faſt, betweene two rockes, ſo faſt as ſhee could not ſtirre: then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with ioyfull hearts, praiſing God went ſafely to ſhore, and ſaued much of their goods, and continued aboue nine moneths, very comfortably, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that their prouiſion of meate, was ſpoiled with the ſalt water, God did feede them plenteouſly with Hogges, Fiſh, Fowles, and other his good creatures, and did multiplie them: for, in that time, there were two children borne and baptized; the one which was a boy they called <hi>Barmudas,</hi> the other which was a girle they called <hi>Barmuda.</hi> Alſo they builded them a ſhippe which they called the
<hi>Deliuerance,</hi> and a Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas which they called the <hi>Patience,</hi> and ſo departed from theſe Ilands ſafely and comfortably on the tenth of <hi>May</hi> 1610. with good ſtore of Hogges fleſh poudred, to carry with them to <hi>Virginia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eleauenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1612. Maſter <hi>Richard Moore</hi> now Deputy Gouernour, ariued ſafely, and with him about 50. ſoules, men, weomen, and children, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habite theſe Ilands, and ſince that time (by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God) diuers other ſhippes out of <hi>England</hi> haue arriued ſafely with good ſupplies: therefore let not the report that hath gone of theſe Ilands diſcourage any of the people of <hi>England</hi> from comming hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:4"/>
            <p>Neither let the feare of forraine inuaſion diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage anie. For; as I am perſwaded, and haue heard Marriners, that haue trauelled farre ſay, the like I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands are not to be found in the world, where men may dwell ſo ſafe from forraine inuaſion, becauſe God hath ſo compaſſed them about with fearefull rockes, as ſhippes are not able to come neere, but in two Channels, that leade into two goodly and large harbours; the one at a place called the <hi>Gurnats head,</hi> the other at a place called <hi>Dauies Point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Channels are ſo narrow and curious, as ſhips muſt come in very leaſurely, one after another, ſo as the forts on both ſides the channels may ſinke them with eaſe, by the helpe of God.</p>
            <p>As it hath pleaſed God, (for the ſafety of thoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands) in their firſt creation, to inuiron them about with fearefull rocks: ſo now in their firſt plantation, it hath pleaſed his holy maieſty, to put into the heart of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Moore,</hi> now deputy Gouernour, to fortifie them within, ſo as in the iudgement of man, they are inuincible.</p>
            <p>At the <hi>Gurnats head</hi> he hath built three forts, and planted them with great peeces, and men to defend them; and at <hi>Dauies Point</hi> he hath builded two forts, and planted them with great peeces and men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them. He hath alſo built diuers other forts to keepe long boates from landing, and to cleer the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, if ſhips ſhould come in.</p>
            <p>If long boates ſhould venture to land any there, they will be but as men caſt away, becauſe ſhips can not come neere to reſcue or helpe any waie: therefore
<pb facs="tcp:6672:5"/>let not feare of forraigne inuaſion, keepe any from comming hither.</p>
            <p>There is great hope that (by the bleſſing of God) men may in time liue very comfortably heere, and grow rich if they will prouide feedes of Indico, &amp;c. and plants of currants, figges, raiſons, mulberry-trees for the ſilk-worms, &amp; vines, that they may haue wine for their owne drinking: I ſay for their owne drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, becauſe wine conſidering the leakeage, trouble, and charge wil be one of the leaſt commodities theſe Ilands will afoord.</p>
            <p>For the preſent, Tobacco is the beſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>And for victuals, if men haue boates, nets, lines, hookes, and ſtriking irons, they may haue good fiſh at all times; as <hi>Rockfiſh, Angell-fiſh, Hogge-fiſh, Amber-fiſh, Cutle-fiſh, Pilat-fiſh, Hedgehog-fiſh, Cunny-fiſh, Old-wiues, Singraies, Snappers, Groopers, Cauallies, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raies, Mullets, Mackerels, Pilchers, Breames, Lobſtars, Turtles, ſharkes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo heere are <hi>Eeles</hi> in freſh water ponds. Riuers here are none, but ponds and welles of very good and holſome water, and a water deſcending from an hill, which floweth and ebbeth with the Sea, and yet drinketh alwaies ſweete, like milke.</p>
            <p>Here is alſo plenty of Sea foules, at one time of the yeere; as about the middle of
<hi>October:</hi> Birds which wee call <hi>Cahouze,</hi> and <hi>Pimlicoes</hi> come in.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cahouze</hi> continue til the beginning of <hi>Iune</hi> in great abundance; they are bigger bodied then a <hi>Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp; of a very firm &amp; good fleſh. They are taken with eaſe, if one doe but ſit downe in a darke night, and
<pb facs="tcp:6672:5"/>make a noiſe, there will more come to him then hee ſhall be able to kill: ſome haue told mee that they haue taken twelue and fowreteene dozen in an how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Cahouze</hi> time is out, other birds cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Noddies,</hi> and <hi>Sandie birds</hi> come in, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue till the latter end of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is no kinde of beaſts but hogges and cattes, &amp; they but in one or two places, which are thought to come at firſt by meanes of ſhippe-wrack. The Hogges were manie, but now are brought to a ſmall number.</p>
            <p>The Calues and Lambes that we brought out of <hi>England,</hi> did proſper exceedingly, till the hunters met with them.</p>
            <p>The Cocks and Hennes wee brought with vs, doe proſper and increaſe much, and are a great comfort vnto vs.</p>
            <p>And now that we haue found out the right ſeaſons of the yeere to ſet Corne, we are like (by the bleſſing of God) to haue plenty of this countrey wheate, which is very good, large and faire, and more hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtrong then our Engliſh wheate.</p>
            <p>Young children doe thriue and grow vp exceeding well, the climate is ſo temperate and agreeable to our Engliſh conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>The Aire is very holſome, and not ſubiect to ſuch contagious infections as it is in
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The longeſt day in the yeere is fowerteene how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the ſhorteſt tenne from ſun to ſun. When it is noone in <hi>England,</hi> it is about eight of the clock in the morning with vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:6"/>
            <p>The ſeaſons of the yeere are two; a hot ſeaſon, that beginneth about the midle of
<hi>Maie,</hi> and continueth till the middeſt of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> all the reſt of the yeere is as a continuall ſpring.</p>
            <p>The heate of Summer is not ſo exſtreame, but it may be well endured.</p>
            <p>Freſh gales of Wind we haue euery daie.</p>
            <p>The greateſt annoiance are flies, for two moneths and a halfe: they are almoſt as buſie in
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Long and drizling raine is ſeldome ſeene, but great ſhowers with great droppes very often.</p>
            <p>Thunder and lightning, do no ſuch hurt here as in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Snow, haile, froſt, thick and foggie miſtes we haue none.</p>
            <p>The night is lighter and more comfortable heere then in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The birds make a noiſe almoſt all night, but not with ſuch pleaſant tunes as the
<hi>Larkes,</hi> and other birds doe in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere is no bird that ſingeth in the daie but the ſparrow, the Robin-red-breſt, &amp; the Robin williams.</p>
            <p>The earth is very fertile, and ſo mellow and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as it needeth neither plowing, nor digging, ſo that after the wood is taken off, and the graſſe and weeds bee burnt and deſtroyed, and the common buſineſſe of fortifying bee once ended, men ſhall liue heere in much caſe, without ſuch moyling and toyling as is in <hi>England.</hi> The greateſt labour will bee in worming and pruning of ſome plants, which children may doe as well, and better then men.</p>
            <p>I wiſh that all they that hereafter ſhal come hither
<pb facs="tcp:6672:6"/>out of <hi>England,</hi> would conſider with themſelues, that theſe Ilands, were neuer inhabited till now, and that therefore they muſt of neceſſity labour hard at firſt, and be contented to endure hardnes and ſome want of many neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>In time (by the grace of God) the ſtore-houſe ſhall be furniſhed with all neceſſaries, for ſuch as haue money, and they that haue not, if they be honeſt and induſtrious, ſhall be truſted: But now in regard that the greateſt part of the people that be heere, came very raſhly and careleſly, not conſidering whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they went, nor what they might in time haue neede of, I thinke that all that can bee brought into the ſtore as yet will be taken vp by them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I aduiſe ſuch as are to come, (to bring euery one that is able) a barrell or two of biskets for his owne eating, till hee haue cleered his ground, and haue wheat of his owne.</p>
            <p>Alſo let them bring oyle, vinager, aquauite, barrell butter, pottes, kettles, frying pannes, triuets, boules, traies, tanckards or pottes to drinke in, pailes to fetch water in, and little barrels or iarres to keepe it in for their drinke. The water is very good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſuch as many doe delight in.</p>
            <p>Alſo let them bring tongs, fireſhouels, bellows, tinder-boxes, brimſtone, flint-ſtones, and ſteeles, ſpits, dripping-pannes, candle ſticks, lampes, locks, ſpades, ſhouels, pick-axes, hatchets, whetſtones; ſawes, hammers, pearcers pincers, and nailes, of all ſorts ſo many as wil ſerue to build a houſe with, and leather to mend their ſhoes, &amp; ſparrowbils, or nailes to driue into them, els the rocks will teare them out quickly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6672:7"/>
            <p>Alſo let them bring bedding: flock-beds are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then feather beds. And for apparrell, for the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, let them bring Canuas, or ſtuffes; blew linen &amp; good buckrom the women doe wiſh for.</p>
            <p>Alſo let them not forget to bring Caſtle ſope, pins points, laſes, needles, threed, thimbles, ſheeres, and ſciſſors. Alſo let them bring ſtrong fiſhing lines, of 12. or
14. faddoms long, and ſom ſmal of whipcords and ſtrong hookes, the biggeſt, and as diuers as they can, and ſome ſmall hooks for breames.</p>
            <p>And aboue all things haue a cate to leaue their ſins beninde them, and come hither as it were into a new world, to lead a new life; and for the comfort of their ſoules let them bring Bibles, and other good bookes: and pack vp all their ſmall ſtuffe in barrels; the barrels wil afterwards ſerue them for many good vſes.</p>
            <p>Idle perſons, and ſuch as are giuen to filching, doe liue heere in great miſery: ſo alſo doe all whoriſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in great diſgrace, hated and loathed of all honeſt people, which maks them weep, and ſigh with teares to wiſh themſelues in <hi>England</hi> againe, and for their comfort, to coole them a little, they are now &amp; then tawed at a boates taile vp and downe the harbour: ſo were a couple ſerued together, a man and a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that came in the ſhip that came in, and ſo haue diuers others.</p>
            <p>Alſo all ſuch as are profaners of the Sabboth, and come to the ſeruice of God but when they liſt, I ſee that God findeth them out, and denieth them his bleſſing.</p>
            <p>All they that haue grace to ſerue God, are ſure to
<pb facs="tcp:6672:7"/>proſper and liue comfortably, becauſe God hath ſaid.
<hi>Behold my ſeruants ſhall eate, and ye ſhall be hungry: behold my ſeruants ſhall drinke, and ye ſhall be thirſty: behold my ſeruants ſhall reioice and ye ſhall be aſhamed: behold my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart, and yee ſhall crie for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houle for vexation of minde.</hi> Iſai 65.13.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him, and vpon them that trust in his mercy, to deliuer their ſoules from death, &amp; to preſerue them in famin.</hi> Pſal. 33.18. &amp; 19</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lions do lacke and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord ſhal want no manner of thing that is good.</hi> Pſal. 34.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wait thou on the Lord, and keepe his way, and he ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt thee, thou ſhalt inherite the land, when the wicked ſhall periſh, thou ſhalt ſee.</hi> Pſal. 37.34:</p>
            <p>The God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord IESVS, the great ſhepheard of the ſheepe, through the blood of the euerlaſting couenant make you perfect in all good workes to doe his will, working in you that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through IESVS CHRIST, to whom be praiſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer, Amen. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.21.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Summer Ilands this</hi>
                  <date>21. <hi>of December.</hi> 1614.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours as his owne, <hi>Lewes Hughes.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
